So I'm going to start this training with the presentation of the RFID technology, which is the source
and origin of many inventions of last decades.
RFID stands for radio Frequency identification, which is a technology used for many applications like
identifying, processing and exchanging information by radio waves between one or more remote elements
like tagging animals, car keys to open the car remotely, bag tags, passport readers, and many other
applications.
It works by attaching a small chip to an object, which can then be read by a scanner or reader.
So the purpose of the RFID technology is to make our life easier and faster while performing daily tasks.
For sure.
It's a better word when you can track inventory levels in real time, locate lost luggage at the airport,
or even monitor the health of patients remotely.
RFID technology makes all this possible and more.
With its ability to automate processes and provide real time data.
RFID is revolutionizing the way we do business and improving our daily lives.
So how this technology works in general.
This rapidly growing technology transmits information wirelessly through the use of radio waves.
RFID requires using a device known as a reader.
The reader is needed to retrieve any data stored on the RFID tag.
A standard RFID tag has a microchip that can contain as much as two gigabytes of information.
Some of the chips used in this technology are smaller than a grain of sand.
The reader device contains an antenna and a small chip to transmit information via the radio frequency
electromagnetic field.
The reader is responsible for picking up identifying information like the unique serial number from
package tags.
The information is picked up via the antenna, which emits radio signals and receives signals back from
These signals are then transmitted in digital format to the appropriate computer system.
What I have just said is a little bit complicated to understand.
If we don't go through a step by step technical explanation, and that's what I'm going to do through
the third section, which will present the communication between a reader, which is also called PCD,
and the contactless card, which is also called PAC.
The technology behind RFID is complicated, but its benefits in terms of tracking and inventory management
makes it a valuable tool for many industries.
About applications.
There are many applications supported by RFID.
For example, in the retail industry.
RFID technology is used to track inventory and reduce theft.
By using RFID tags on products, retailers can quickly and accurately monitor their stock levels and
prevent loss due to theft.
This is not only saves time, but also improves customer satisfaction by ensuring that products are
always in stock.
In health care.
RFID technology is used to improve patient safety and streamline processes.
RFID tags can be attached to patient wristbands to ensure that they receive the correct medication and
treatment.
Additionally, RFID technology can be used to track medical equipment and supplies, reducing the risks
of errors and improving efficiency.
When we talk about RFID systems or RLC circuits, the term of frequency is always showing up, and you
can even say that it's one of the basics of this technology.
In fact, RFID system can be broken down by the frequency band within which they operate.
They are often characterized by their operating frequency.
Band frequency refers to the size of the radio waves used to communicate between system components.
RFID systems throughout the world operate in low frequency, high frequency, and ultra high frequency
bands.
Some people call higher frequency.
Super high frequency.
Radio waves behave differently at each of these frequencies, and there are advantages and disadvantages
associated with using each frequency band.
To start the low frequency band, I mean the Lf band covers frequencies from 30kHz to 135kHz.
Typically, Lf rid systems operate at 125kHz.
This frequency band provides a short read range of ten centimeter and has lower read speed than the
higher frequencies.
Then the high frequency band runs from 3 to 30MHz.
Most HF RFID systems operate at 1350 six megahertz, with read ranges between 10cm and 1m.
And here we are talking about NFC systems.
HF systems I mean high frequency systems experience moderate sensitivity to interference.
HF.
RFID is commonly used for ticketing, payment, and data transfer applications.
There are several HF RFID standards in place, such as the ISO 15,693 standard for tracking items,
and ISO 18,092 standards for near-field communication.
NFC, a short range technology that is commonly used for data exchange between devices.
Other high frequency standards, which is very important as it will be the one that we are going to
talk about, is the ISO 14,443 type A and ISO 14 443 type B, and also ISO 14,443 standards for Mifare
technology, which used in smart cards and proximity cards.
NFC is best described as a subset of RFID.
NFC devices operate at the same frequency as high frequency RFID readers and tags.
1350 six megahertz.
But unlike RFID devices and tags, NFC does not have a range from 25m to 100m.
Instead, NFC takes advantage of the short read range limitation of its radio frequency.
Because NFC devices must be in close proximity to each other no more than a few centimeters apart.
NFC has become the top choice for secure communication between consumer devices such as smartphones.
Radio frequency identification a contactless one way communication method at varying distances.
NFC, which is near-field communication, allows for two way communication and requires action by the
user.
By the way, in some parts of this training, I'm going to present and detail every aspect defined in
the ISO 14,443 standard, which is the Qi standard at the basis of contactless communication.
Then after this ranges of frequency, we have the ultra high frequency band, which covers the range
from 300MHz to 3GHz.
Ultra high frequency RFID is used in a wide variety of applications, ranging from retail inventory
management to pharmaceutical to wireless device configuration.
Active RFID systems typically operate in the ultra high frequency band and offer a range of up to 100m.
In general, active tags are used on large objects such as real cards, big reusable containers, and
other assets that need to be tracked over long distance.
So there are three types of RFID systems active systems, passive systems, and battery assisted passive
systems.
Be I mean VIP systems.
Regarding the active RFID systems.
In fact, in active RFID systems, tags have their own transmitter and power source.
Usually the power source is a battery.
In fact, active tags broadcast their own signal to transmit the information stored on their microchips.
Active RFID systems typically operate in the ultra high frequency band and offer a range of up to 100m.
In general, active tags are used on large objects such as real cars.
Big usable containers.
There are two main types of active tags transponders and beacons.
Transponders are woken up when they receive a radio signal from a reader, and then power on and respond
by transmitting a signal back.
Because transponders do not actively radiate radio waves until they receive a reader signal, they conserve
battery life.
Beacons are often used in real time locating systems.
Rtls in order to track the precise location of an asset continuously.
Unlike transponders, beacons are not powered on by the reader's signal.
Instead, they emit signals at preset intervals.
Depending on the level of locating accuracy required, beacons can be set to emit signals every few
seconds or once a day.
Each beacons signal is received by a reader antenna that are positioned around the perimeter of the
area being monitored, and communicates the tags, information, and position.
Then we have the passive RFID systems.
In passive RFID systems, the reader and reader antenna send a radio signal to the tag.
The RFID tag then uses the transmitted signal to power on and reflect energy back to the reader.
Passive RFID systems can operate in the low frequency, high frequency, or ultra high frequency radio
bands.
As passive system range are limited by the power of tags backscatter, they are typically less than
ten metres.
By the way, when I say backscatter, I mean the radio signal reflected from the tag back to the reader.
Because passive tags do not require a power source or transmitter and only require a tag chip and antenna,
they are cheaper, smaller, and easier to manufacture than active tags.
Passive tags can be packaged in many different ways depending on the specific RFID application requirements.
For instance, they may be mounted on a substrate or sandwiched between an adhesive layer and a paper
label to create smart RFID labels.
Passive tags may also be embedded in a variety of devices or packages to make the tag resistant to extreme
temperature or harsh cleaning chemicals.
So the third type of the systems is battery assisted passive systems.
A battery assisted passive RFID tag is a type of passive tag which is incorporating a crucial active
tag feature.
While most passive RFID tags use the energy from the RFID reader signal to power on tags, chip and
backscatter to the reader.
BRP tags use an integrated power source, usually a battery, to power on the chip, so all of the captured
energy from the reader can be used for backscatter.
Unlike transponders, BRP tags do not have their own transmitter.
And here we are.
We have the summary of our first training.
So RFID is a technology for identifying, processing and exchanging information by radio waves between
one or more remote elements.
It's a wireless communication between a reader and a card or tag that uses electromagnetic coupling.
RFID systems can operate in Lf low frequency, high frequency, and ultra high frequency NFC.
A subset of RFID operates at 1350 six megahertz.
The ISO 14,143 standard is the one that defines the communication protocols of communication.
Active RFID systems have their own transmitter and power source and passive RFID system, where the
reader antenna sends a radio signal to the tag.